Previously on "The Ark"...
I always thought
Black Thorn was a rumor.
This is a genetic library
of selected
animalia DNA samples
from Earth.
You did all of this
in your sleep?
Everyone on Homebase
loves you.
And I love you.
I love you too.
I saw an opportunity
when I detected
the dormant chip,
so I took it.
That thing put you
in my head, didn't it?
We built a nice colony
called Homebase 1.
Trail stops here.
There is indeed something
in that lake.
It's "EF1."
Must have been shot down.
What have you found?
Bodies.
There were survivors.
Zed.
I'm so sorry
about this, mate.
We cross-referenced each
ID with the EF manifest.
These bodies are from "EF1,"
but I'm relieved to say
your son is not one of them.
Don't be.
My son's body is likely
at the bottom of that lake.
I really hope
that's not true.
I want to know exactly
how my people died
and who buried them.
Is it possible
they were buried
by other "EF1" survivors?
I mean, maybe they're
still out there, alive.
No.
They would've come to us
as soon as we arrived.
I've finished reviewing
the autopsy results.
They have all been dead
for about 22 months,
and they were killed
the same way...
By gunshot.
I want answers.
We'll get them.
Dr. Marsh said the bodies--
What type of weapon
systems were used?
Ammunition?
What was the motive?
Zed, Dr. Marsh said
the bodies died two years ago.
I'm aware of that.
You know who arrived
here two years ago?
"Ark 11."
You think this was
Ves and Black Thorn?
Could be.
This was the secret
she was hiding,
and Hammond found out.
It would explain
why she killed him
and framed Strickland.
But does that mean
she shut down the "EF1" ship?
If she did,
the rest of "Ark 11" would
all be complicit.
I trusted you, Garnet.
I trusted that all
of the GSA would
fall behind you
and choose peace.
I'm sorry, Zed, but I--
Captain Avega!
Captain Avega, I can't
control the actions of others.
I didn't even know there was
a Black Thorn unit here.
But I can tell you this.
If they or any other
GSA personnel are responsible
for the murder of your people,
they'll pay the consequences.
How?
We'll follow due process.
Due process?
Are you kidding?
More than 200 of my people
were murdered.
A crime far beyond the scope
of anything that would
require due process.
For now, we need to
still make sure everyone
at Homebase is safe.
"Ark 16" is disembarking
as we speak.
And we still don't know
who the Black Thorn are.
Okay, let's start
by talking to Kimi.
Since EF Hunters was
a division of Black Thorn,
maybe she can help.
I didn't know Kimi was
an EF hunter.
This just keeps getting
better and better.
This is when we were
still at war.
Her job was
to murder people like me.
Again, we were at war.
Since then, Kimi has more than
proven herself non-partisan.
I would trust her
with my life and yours.
Just the same,
I don't want her
anywhere near me.
Captain Avega,
why don't you go supervise
the divers at the lake?
You can help them identify
the rest of the bodies.
Strickland and I will
handle everything else.
Fine.
But let me give you
a word of advice.
Former EF security
are the only ones we know
for sure are not Black Thorn.
I will tell my men to follow
yours and Felix's orders
while you investigate.
But I would relieve
all former GSA security
personnel of their duties.
Hey.
Where are you going?
Uh, oh, um, I--
Tell her you want
to stretch your legs.
I'm just gonna go
and stretch my legs.
Don't you wanna shower first?
Rest? We just got home.
Don't you worry
about me, my love.
I'm absolutely fine, okay?
I am worried about you.
You've been through a lot,
and you need to rest.
You need to go now.
You know what?
I'm--I'm actually
feeling kind of hungry.
So I'm just gonna head
down to Landing Pad,
quickly grab something,
all right?
Okay, I'll come with you.
- Absolutely not.
- Uh, no.
No, no, no. It's fine.
It's fine.
You, uh--
you wanna stay here
and get unpacked, get settled.
So, uh, yeah, you stay here,
and I will be right back, okay?
Mwah!
Hey. Hey, listen.
You need to back off, okay?
I can't think with you always
hovering and in my ear.
You don't need to think.
You need to do as I say.
Something's
different about you.
It's like you're--
you're deeper in my brain
or something.
Follow me.
Where are we going?
To the part
of me that's sick.
Come.
Let me show you.
Hi.
You're back.
Yeah.
Oh.
I missed you.
Oh, God, I missed you too.
Really?
Really.
Uh, Sanji.
Hmm?
I've got to
tell you something.
Milan is dead.
What?
You remember he had
internal bleeding
when you left.
Yeah, but--
It was manageable at first,
but things took a turn
for the worse quickly,
and he coded.
We--we were unable
to resuscitate him.
Come here.
You okay?
Um--
You're relieved?
Relieved?
You think I'm relieved
that he's dead?
No, no, of course not.
That's not what I meant.
I--
I don't know.
Um, what?
For the record,
I disavowed Black Thorn
as soon as I was exposed
as an EF hunter.
I've been loyal
solely to you, "Ark 1,"
and Homebase ever since.
We know.
Do you know where
Ves might be hiding?
No.
I didn't even know
she was Black Thorn.
As I understand it,
you were each relegated
to a specific Ark?
Yes, in isolated units
with our own codes.
So have no idea who
"Ark 11's" other members are.
Did every ship have
the same number of Thorns?
On "Ark 15," Lati and I
were the only ones.
The larger groups
could be 12, 15.
And they were all led
by commanders.
- Like Ves?
- Mm-hmm.
So whoever
the "Ark 11" members are...
They're all loyal to Ves.
Do you have any idea how
she was able to summon them all
so quickly to help her escape?
Every active-duty Thorn
keeps a small device
on their person at all times,
an encrypted beacon that can
summon all members of the unit.
When triggered, all the other
Thorns meet at that location.
So we should find
Ves and then--
Use her beacon
to smoke out her team.
Eva?
Just get her out of here.
You lied to me.
No, I didn't.
You said you were going
to a bar to get food.
Eva, listen to me.
You need to go, okay?
You need to go now.
You're scaring me.
I want to bring
you to infirmary.
Listen to me.
I've grown deeper
into your brain,
and I can make you do
whatever I want.
So tell her to leave.
You can't be here.
Hey. It's me.
You can talk to me.
- I can't.
I'm sorry it had
to come to this.
Kill her.
Now.
It's okay.
I'm so sorry.
I can't believe
what I'm seeing.
What is it?
You know how Maddox put
those chips in our brains
when we first arrived here?
Well, Brice's chip
has activated
and become entangled in strands
of new neural tissue.
It has to do with whatever
happened to me on Ross.
Yeah, but your chip
looked completely normal
after we rescued you,
which means the strands grew
over the last few days.
Maybe that explains
your behavior from today.
Maybe the chip is
controlling you.
So remove the chip.
Trust me, you don't
want to do that.
We can't remove it now
without it killing you.
I like her.
But there must be a way
to shut down the chip.
But how?
I don't know.
I wonder if Alicia could
help us tap into
the software somehow.
Worth a try.
Alicia to infirmary.
It's urgent.
None of them will
ever get me out.
Leave now before I make
you hurt someone.
- Doc?
- Yeah?
I need you to restrain me.
- What?
- Sorry?
Look, if your theory
is correct,
I might not be able
to control my actions.
Are you sure?
Do it.
Fast.
Okay.
Hey, we're going
to figure this out.
Oh, trust me, you're not.
I always thought Black Thorn
was an old wives tale.
Don't know anything about it.
Why do you ask?
Captain, we have
reason to believe
that Ves Ilic was a commander
of a Black Thorn unit
on your ship.
- On "Ark 11"?
- Yes.
There's no way.
Why do you say that?
I knew everything that
happened on that ship.
Well, we think she
might have shot down "EF1."
How?
"Ark 11" had no weapons.
And it's not like
she could've secretly been
hiding something big enough
to shoot down a whole ship.
I'm sorry, but this all
just sounds ridiculous.
Okay, then.
Thank you for your time.
We need to talk to Angus.
Angus? Why?
Angus.
Have you found any evidence
of sunflowers
growing here naturally?
No.
Which is a bummer when you
think about their impact
on soil health
and the biofuel potential.
Let me just check the, uh--
Doesn't look like any other
Arks carried them either.
Why do you ask?
Yeah, what do sunflowers
have to do with "EF1"?
The former captain
of "Ark 11" was
pruning sunflowers.
If there aren't any here and
no one brought them on Earth,
then where did he get them?
You think he brought
them in the DNA vault?
Uh, there's no vault
on "Ark 11."
Yes, that's what
we wanted you to think.
No one knows
the room even exists,
which makes it a good place
for Ves to hide.
Mm-hmm.
Well, all the vaults were
built in the same place--
behind the wall
in OT section of G Deck.
Okay.
"Ark 11's" G Deck
is now Building 14B.
Let's go.
Mr. Trust.
The divers found
the server box from "EF1."
Oh, hi.
Hi.
Is the data salvageable?
Who knows?
I'm sure as hell gonna try.
Hopefully we'll find
the captain's log
so we can learn
what really happened.
Great.
Let me know the second
you find anything.
- Check it out.
- Uh-huh.
- Let's go over there.
- Oh!
- Angus?
- Yeah?
Uh, can I talk
to you outside?
Yeah.
So I've been automatic
writing all night.
You can understand
all of this?
Yes.
I mean, I can't speak or
understand the spoken language,
but I think I can understand
enough of the written language
to be able to communicate
with the people in the caves.
So we have to go
back to the caves.
Why?
What if you were
right all along?
Maybe they're trying
to tell us something.
Okay, just let me
get a security detail
together to go with us and--
- No.
If we bring a bunch
of strangers down there,
the people down there
might not let us in.
Okay, but we should at least
tell Mr. Trust and Felix.
I don't think we should.
They'll never let us go alone.
So you're saying you wanna
go, just us, no weapons,
to see the people
who kidnapped us?
Yes.
I mean, I can always turn
my implants on if I have to.
Hey, Dr. Kabir?
Could I have a word?
Um--
It's private.
Of course.
What's wrong?
I don't want to get
anyone in trouble.
Okay.
Whatever it is,
you can tell me.
When Petrovic flatlined,
Dr. Marsh hesitated--
for too long.
What do you mean hesitated?
He just kind of
stood there, staring.
Almost like he was
debating what to do.
Then when I came over,
he snapped back to business.
You did the right
thing telling me,
but can we keep this
between us?
Of course.
Thank you.
Clear.
How did you find me?
Put your gun down,
and we'll tell you.
We just wanna talk.
Okay?
It's just that--
I don't trust you.
Hand over your unit beacon.
Now.
Kimi?
What happened to
"Once a Thorn, always a Thorn?"
Who's in
your Thorn unit, Ves?
I don't know what
you're talking about.
Then rot in here.
Let's go.
Well, that was successful.
How are we gonna find
the rest of them now?
I have an idea.
You really think
Milan was Black Thorn?
Well, he was close to Ves.
Um, okay, but why
do you need me here?
We're looking
for a beacon they carry.
It's relatively small, gray,
and shaped kind of like--
Kind of like this.
It's password protected.
That's why you're here, Sanji.
Four digits,
using 1 through 6.
Try 6161.
It's the address
of his first house.
61--
nope.
Okay.
Um--hmm.
Try 1122.
November 22nd.
Month and day he was
sworn in as a cop.
His proudest moment.
Thank you, Sanji.
I don't think there's
a way to disable the chip
without killing Brice.
Maybe if we can
figure out how
the programming got into
his chip in the first place--
It was that thing
that was connected
behind my ear on Ross.
- Shut up.
There's nothing on the MRI
where the tube was connected.
It's just scar tissue.
Or maybe it's not.
Okay, okay.
Look, I get it.
You're mad I made you
go into the woods
and try to hurt
your girlfriend.
But I am doing
what I have to do.
What's that?
It's a bioelectric
impedance probe.
Okay, what's it for?
Well, if I'm correct...
The scar tissue is conductive.
- Shit.
- What?
It's not scar tissue.
It's some sort of
electro-organic strand
that was left there
by the thing that
connected behind Brice's ear.
So this is how we can
access the chip?
Exactly.
Start rigging a contact.
This isn't just about me.
Trust me, if they disappear me,
you will never be the same.
Do you have any plan
on how to get inside?
I was sort of hoping
they would just--
Do that.
It's my clothes.
Maybe it's
a gesture of goodwill?
It means hello.
I think.
I don't like this.
Come on.
- Hey.
- Hmm.
How's it going with Brice?
It's complicated.
What can I do to help?
Nothing.
Okay, Sanji.
What's going on?
You've been
avoiding me all day.
I can't do this right now.
Do what?
Okay.
If it's because
of what I said about Milan--
It's not what you said.
It's what you did,
or didn't do.
What are you talking about?
You killed him.
No, I didn't.
I checked
the medical records.
Milan flatlined,
and you waited 12 seconds
before trying to resuscitate.
12 seconds.
I was trying to be thoughtful
about the plan of action--
Bullshit!
You knew exactly
what was gonna happen.
Even if I hadn't waited,
it probably wouldn't have
made a difference.
What the hell
kind of argument is that?
I didn't mean for him to die.
But you're not sorry.
No.
No, I'm not.
Thanks for coming.
Yeah, the water in that
lake was near freezing,
so it preserved
the bodies fairly well.
I was able to pull up
the manifest
from the server we recovered.
So we've been able to identify
most of them, but...
we still need you to try
and ID the rest.
I'm really sorry you have
to be the one to do this, but--
Who else would do it?
Lieutenant Efram Womby.
Corporal Albert Flink.
Leonard...
Avega.
My son.
Can I join you?
I'm so sorry about your son.
I really wanted to blame you.
Or at least the GSA.
But the truth is,
it's my fault.
Leo was an artist.
He was happy
painting alone in his room,
even when the world was--
was crumbling.
He wasn't like me or anyone
I knew, for that matter.
I couldn't understand him.
I'm not a parent.
Hell, I didn't
even have parents.
But isn't that how
most parents feel,
like they don't
understand their kids?
Hmm.
My wife always said
I was too hard on him.
Your wife?
Sheila, the love of my life.
She died when Leo was 12.
And I was left to raise
a boy I didn't understand.
I am so sorry.
I pushed him to join the EF,
practically forced him.
Told him he had to help
make a difference,
and he hated me for it.
I doubt that.
Oh, no, he did.
And because he hated me,
I assigned him
to "EF1" instead of my ship,
so I didn't have to
look him in the eye.
And now--
Zed, hey.
His death is not your fault.
I was his father.
It was my job to protect him.
You did protect him.
If you hadn't put him on "EF1,"
he probably would have died
two years earlier
with everyone else
left behind on Earth.
I should've put him
on "EF2" with me.
He'd still be alive.
You could not have
predicted what would happen.
His death is not your fault.
Then who the hell's
fault is it?
James, there is still time
to stop this.
Okay, this wire
can transmit signals
to and from your
conductive tissue
to access whatever
programming's in the chip.
Buddy.
Okay, try now.
I'm in.
I saved your life.
Don't you owe me the same?
It worked?
Uh, well, sort of.
I can see the code,
but I can't
recognize it at all.
What do you mean?
It's not binary.
It's ternary.
Base three.
I can't make sense of it.
It's--it's totally foreign.
What are you asking?
I asked his name.
But I can't translate
his response.
Guess we'll just keep
calling him John Doe.
How do you communicate
with each other?
He says he spoke to them.
But I didn't hear anything.
They must talk in a frequency
outside our hearing range.
It kind of makes sense.
He has different
hearing and vocal cords.
Ask them why we were kidnapped.
"You break."
You break what?
It's that symbol.
It's the only one
I can't translate.
What does it mean?
Did you trigger it?
- No.
Who made the call?
- Against the wall!
- Masks off.
And keep your hands
where we can see them.
Okay, I've combed through
everything on the chip.
The code is indecipherable.
But if we can purge
the code from the chip,
there may be a chance that
Brice will go back to normal.
"Purge" means I will be gone.
Do you understand?
Guys, maybe we shouldn't
delete it all, you know?
We might need
the information later.
Yeah, that's true.
With all
these questions looming
about Ross and Homebase,
it could be valuable.
I am valuable.
But I'm of no use to you
if I'm not in your head.
You're right.
Instead of purging it,
I'll move the data
into an air-gapped device.
That way it can't infiltrate
our computer system.
But the software will
be completely
out of his head, right?
Right.
It'll be here instead.
Please.
James, you don't know
what you're doing.
Alicia...
do it.
James.
James, please.
You will regret this.
This is for the best.
Who is he talking to?
I don't know.
I will make you regret this.
Goodbye.
The transfer is complete.
How do you feel, James?
I, uh--
Thank you.
Just let him rest.
Let him rest.
Here's how it's gonna go.
You're going to tell us exactly
what happened two years ago.
The only way
I'm telling you anything
is if you let my team go.
They were only
following orders.
Absolutely not.
But I can promise you this.
If you don't help us right now,
your team will suffer
grave consequences.
Okay.
Ves, we can't make a deal until
we know exactly what happened.
Fine.
Start talking.
We killed those
"EF1" survivors.
Avega, you have to understand
that, at that time,
they were still the enemy.
We were in the fog of war.
The mission was standard--
do a sweep and make sure
there were no hostiles here
before "Ark 11" came down.
We were about to turn around
and go back to the ship
when we smelled smoke.
Smoke?
Camp smoke.
We followed it
and found a group of people
living in the woods somehow.
They're EF.
Fire!
So you just killed
all those people?
We were outnumbered.
They were going to kill us--
You do not know that!
Avega, please.
Why didn't you tell us
any of this before?
Why murder Hammond
to keep this secret?
Because of you two,
Sharon and Zed.
- Oh, come on.
- Wait, me?
When you came here,
you had made peace.
I wasn't going to blow it
by revealing who we had killed.
No, it doesn't
make any sense.
You buried the bodies.
You wanted to cover it up
right away.
Weapons.
What?
There were
no weapons recovered
from that pile of bodies.
The EF soldiers
were unarmed
when you found them,
weren't they?
You mowed down
all those unarmed people?
I wanna know how
you shot down "EF1,"
how you killed hundreds
of innocent people
on board that ship.
Tell me!
I didn't--I didn't know
anything about that.
Avega!
You're a liar!
She is a murderer.
Yes, she is.
But don't let her
turn you into one.
Ian, if you've come
to try and calm me down--
No, no, no. No.
Just to give you
some information.
The server shut down
two weeks before
"Ark 11" arrived at Homebase.
I'm not sure I follow.
The server shut down
because the ship went down
before Ves or "Ark 11"
were even here.
So Ves was telling the truth.
I don't know
who shot down "EF1,"
but it wasn't her.
You're saying you've
been seeing and hearing
Doc Morozov this whole time?
Yep.
Thanks.
Yeah.
And she felt so real.
That must've been some
insanely advanced AI.
- Mm.
- Yeah.
Yep.
She saved my life.
Made it seem like I was
supposed to save her too.
Something about, like, fixing
a part of her here on Homebase.
A part of her?
What does that mean?
I don't know.
Never got that far.
Oh, man, I am just so, so happy
to feel like myself again,
you know?
Thank you, both of you,
for everything, really.
I'm so happy you're okay.
Oh, oh, okay.
You're friendly.
One of the new doctors.
Yeah.
Uh, we haven't met, have we?
I'm James.
James Brice.
Nice to meet you.
Um--
What?
So Ves didn't
shoot down the ship.
No, she couldn't have.
I despise her,
but she didn't kill my boy.
What happens when we meet
the people who did?
I think we already have.
There's only one group
of people that could have
been here when "EF1" arrived.
The people in the caves.
Wait.
If they were able to
shoot down a spaceship, then--
They must have access
to a massive weapon.
Fix?
I don't understand.
Heal.
Fix what? Heal what?
I don't know.
Fix or death.
Hey.
Is he saying--
If we don't fix it,
they'll kill us.